William A. Bernrieder Collection
University of Houston Libraries
William A. Bernrieder Collection
1917-1988
Bernrieder, William A.
As an assistant to Houston mayor Oscar Holcombe, William A. Bernrieder spearheaded a successful local drive to have a Navy heavy cruiser named for the City of Houston. He supported the USS Houston (CA-30) during her years of service as a member of the Cruiser Houston Committee, and following the ship's sinking, continued to memorialize the ship and interact with surviving crew members. This collection consists primarily of materials related to the campaign to have a ship named for the city of Houston, and the history of the USS Houston (CA-30). Additional materials are related to the 1936 visit to Houston of President Franklin D. Roosevelt.
18 boxes; 8.6 linear feet
1979-001
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
William Anton Bernrieder was born on June 22, 1900. He attended St. Joseph School in 1906, then Annunciation Church School. He then attended St. Thomas College (now St. Thomas High School) after a period at St. Mary's Seminary. William Bernrieder completed three years of law school at Houston Law School.
In 1923, William Bernrieder began six years of service to Oscar Holcombe, the mayor of Houston. During this time he began his work toward having a ship in the U.S. Navy named after Houston. In 1927 he was appointed to the Cruiser Houston Committee, which coordinated the drive towards obtaining a cruiser named "Houston." Thousands of letters and telegrams were sent to Washington as part of the crusade, which was successful. A heavy cruiser named for the city of Houston was launched on Sept. 7, 1927. Once Bernrieder and the other members of the committee had succeeded in having a ship named for the city, the committee worked toward supporting the ship and its crew through gifts and other means.
From 1930 to 1933 Bernrieder served as the assistant to Rear Admiral Richard E. Byrd. As part of his duties, he accompanied Byrd on a nationwide speaking tour. During this period, however, Bernrieder paid careful attention to the Cruiser Houston and continued to be involved in supporting the vessel.
Bernrieder was also involved in politics, serving as Executive Secretary for local arrangements for the National Democratic Convention, held in Houston in 1928. He was also involved in arrangements for President Franklin Roosevelt's trip to Houston in 1936.
Receiving his commission in 1926, Bernrieder served for 22 years in the Naval Reserve. He spent five years on active duty with the Navy during World War II, serving on the staffs of five admirals.
Following World War II Bernrieder was involved in the real estate business in Houston, although he continued his interest in the history of the USS Houston (CA-30), which had been lost in the Battle of Sunda Strait on Feb. 28/March 1, 1942. Bernrieder collected information related to the history of the ship as well as efforts to retrieve items from the sunken vessel.
Bernrieder died on October 18, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The William A. Bernrieder Collection has a great deal of information about the history of the USS Houston (CA-30) as well as the USS Texas and Franklin Roosevelt's visit to Houston in 1936. Bernrieder corresponded with many of the leading businessmen and politicians in Houston during his lifetime, as well as officers in the Navy. The collection dates from 1917- 1988, with the bulk of the material dating from 1929-1936 and from 1970-1986.
Bernrieder kept a considerable amount of material from his early work regarding having a ship named for the city of Houston and added additional materials to his files throughout his life. There are also a number of items from A. D. Simpson, who was heavily involved in the Cruiser Houston Committee as well.
For the most part, arrangement has followed Bernrieder's subject files with some modification. File folders that could be sub-divided chronologically or by sub-topic have been refiled. Also, folders with materials covering the same topic which had originally been filed separately have been brought together. Because Bernrieder followed a subject arrangement for his files, correspondence is scattered throughout the collection.
There are a number of series within the collection, based on subject with the exception of the Correspondence series. The series are: Correspondence, Democratic Party, Franklin Roosevelt's Visit, USS Houston Campaign, USS Houston, USS Texas, Publications, and Miscellaneous. Within each series are additional topics, arranged alphabetically by subject heading. The largest series is the USS Houston series, which chronicles the history of the USS Houston.
Later additions to the collection have been incorporated into the subject files arrangement where possible. However, large amounts of correspondence which were donated after the initial gift of materials in 1979 have been given a simple chronological arrangement. Most of the correspondence in those files discusses the USS Houston and related matters, although there is one letter, dated August 23, 1977 which includes Bernrieder's recollections of the Camp Logan riots in Houston in 1917.
For related materials, see the Cruiser Houston Collection, which includes materials donated by crew members from the USS Houston and their families and friends. A large portion of the photographs in the Cruiser Houston Collection were given by Bernrieder, and have remained in that collection.
Subjects (Persons)
Bernrieder, William A.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945
Subjects (Organizations)
Cruiser Houston Committee; Houston (Cruiser: CA-30)
Subjects
Java Sea, Battle of the, Indonesia, 1942; World War, 1939-1945 -- Naval operations, American; Sunda Strait, Battle of, Indonesia, 1942; Democratic National Convention (1928: Houston, Tex.)
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition
The collection was given to the library by William A. Bernrieder, Executive Secretary of the Cruiser Houston Committee, in 1979. Additional items were given by Mr. Bernrieder throughout the 1980s.
Detailed Description
- Correspondence, 1924-1986, (643 items) (Box 1, Folder 1-18)
  This is an artificial series, which incorporates all of the correspondence from later gifts by Bernrieder to the collection. The correspondence follows a chronological arrangement scheme. Most of the correspondence relates to the USS Houston and Mr. Bernrieder's interest in the collection. Materials from the 1980s include a great deal of correspondence with Otto Schwarz, founder of the USS Houston Survivors Association. Bernrieder corresponded with a number of officers in the United States Navy, as well as Texas and Houston politicians.
  - Correspondence, 1924-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- USS Houston Campaign, 1927-1942, (302 items) (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
  This series relates primarily to the campaign to have a cruiser named after the city of Houston. The bulk of the materials is correspondence. A great deal of related materials may be found both the USS Houston series as well as the Correspondence series. A small amount of information relating to the drive for a second Cruiser Houston is in this series (for related materials, see the files in the USS Houston series under USS Houston (CL-81)).
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Organizations, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Press Materials, 1927-1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Resolutions, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Resolutions, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Resolutions, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Resolutions, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Resolutions, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- USS Houston, 1927-1985, (5,452 items) (Box 2-11, 18, Framed, Oversize)
  This is the largest of the series and focuses primarily on the USS Houston (CA-30). The material in this section includes correspondence, clippings, telegrams, photographs, and other materials. The bulk of the series dates from 1927-1936, focusing on the beginnings of the USS Houston, its launch, and early visits to the city of Houston.
  The correspondence relating to the launching of the USS Houston is arranged chronologically. Invitations were sent to all major naval officers, many Houston and Texas politicians, members of the U.S. Cabinet, and dignitaries from Congress and from other states. Replies were received by nearly all those invited.
  There are some materials relating to the two ships which followed the USS Houston (CA-30). Another ship named the USS Houston was launched in 1943. Materials relating to that ship may be found in the USS Houston (CL-81) files. Materials relating to the nuclear submarine, the USS Houston (SSN-713), may be located under that heading. Clippings have been placed in files, but have not been placed in order. Particular care must be taken when using the clippings as most are on highly acidic, fragile newsprint.
  - Address, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Admiral's Flag (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Admirals--Photographs (9) (Box Framed)
  - Allin, B. C. and Mrs., 1930-1960 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bell Presentation, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bernrieder Collection, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Blue Bonnet, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Blue Bonnet, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Book, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Book, 1961-1964 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Book, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Book Proposal--Milner, Samuel, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Byrd, Admiral and Mrs., 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Christmas, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Christmas, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Christmas, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Christmas--Photographs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Christmas--Photographs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Christmas--Photographs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Christmas--Photographs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Christmas--Photographs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Christmas--Solicitation, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Collection Luncheon--Photographs, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Collection Luncheon--Photographs, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Collection Luncheon--Photographs, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Commanding Officers, 1927-1930 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Commanding Officers, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Commanding Officers, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Commanding Officers, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Commanding Officers, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Commanding Officers, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Commanding Officers, 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Commanding Officers, 1943-1962 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Commanding Officers--Photographs (17) (Box Framed)
  - Commission SSN-713, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1933 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1959 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee, 1927-1957 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Correspondence, 1929-1937 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Correspondence, 1955-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Finances, 1926-1929 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Finances, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Finances, 1930-1941 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Finances--Bank Books, 1934-1941 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Members, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Minutes, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cruiser Houston Committee--Resolutions, 1928-1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cruiser Houston Room--Photograph, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Documentary Expedition, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Flags (Box 18)
  - Gifts, 1930-1933 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Gifts, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Gifts, 1934-1936 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gifts, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Gifts, 1936-1974 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - George R. Brown Room Dedication, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Houston Centennial, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - History, 1932-1960 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - History, 1961-1963 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - History, 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - History, 1968-1974 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - History, 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - History of CL-81, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Information, 1927-1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Information--Brochures, 1951-1973 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Information--News Releases, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Jahnke, Ernest Lee, 1930-1933 (Box Oversize)
  - Launch SSN-713, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Launch SSN-713--Invitations, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Launching--Clippings, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Launching--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Launching--Correspondence--Sponsors, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Launching--Invitations, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Launching--Invitations--Miscellaneous, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Launching--Lists, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Launching--Miscellaneous, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Launching--Other Ships, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Launching--Other Ships, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Launching--Other Ships, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Launching--Other Ships, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Launching--Replies, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Launching--Thank yous, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Loss of Ship, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Loss of Ship--Memorial, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Lost Battalion Association, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Lost Battalion Association, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Lost Battalion Association, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Maps (Box 18)
  - McKie, Ronald, 1960-1962 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - McKie, Ronald, 1963-1968 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Medal of Honor, [1942] (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Memorial, 1975-1979 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Memorial, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Memorial Room, Houston Public Library, 1930-1978 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Model, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Model--Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Model--Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Model--Photographs, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Model--Photographs--Drummond, Joseph, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Model--Photographs--Drummond, Joseph, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Model--Photographs--Drummond, Joseph, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Model--Photographs--Presentation, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Model Presentation, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Model Presentation, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Model Purchase, 1942-1979 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Navy Day, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Navy Day--Correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Navy Day--Miscellaneous, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Navy Day--Planning, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Oral Histories, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Photograph, 1930 (Box Oversize)
  - Photograph, undated (Box Framed)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Photographs--Launching CL-81, 1943 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Photographs--Reunion, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Photographs--Reunion, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Photographs--Reunion, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Photographs--Reunion, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Photographs--Roosevelt, Henry L., undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Photographs--Ship's Plans, undated (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Photographs--Ship's Plans, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - USS Houston (CL-81), 1942 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - USS Houston (CL-81)--Bond Drive, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Thousand Houston Volunteers --Ceremony, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Thousand Houston Volunteers--Ceremony, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Thousand Houston Volunteers--Crew, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - USS Houston (CL-81)--Launch, 1942-1943 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Ship's Plans, undated (Box Framed)
  - Shrine Proposal, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Silver Service--Clippings, 1906-1967 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Silver Service--Correspondence, 1927-1929 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Silver Service--Correspondence, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Silver Service--Correspondence, 1929-1942 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Silver Service--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Silver Service--Photographs, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Silver Service--Photographs, Other, [1929] (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Silver Service--Photographs, Other, [1929] (Box 18)
  - Silver Service--Recovery, 1943-1974 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Survivors' Roster, undated (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Thousand Houston Volunteers Monument, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Thousand Houston Volunteers Monument--Photograph, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Visit, 1934-1935 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Visit, 1938-1939 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Visit, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Visit, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Visit--Committees, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Visit--Communications with Ship, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Visit--Finances, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Visit--Letters of Thanks, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Visit--Miscellaneous, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Visit--Navy Day, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Visit--Officers' Rosters, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Visit--Publicity, [1934] (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Visit--Radio Address, 1929-1930 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Wait, J. Russell, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Wait, J. Russell, 1939 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Wait, J. Russell, 1956 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Winslow, Walter, 1967-1969 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Winslow, Walter, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Winslow, Walter, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Winslow, Walter, 1975-1977 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Winslow, Walter, undated (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Democratic Party, 1927-1967, (119 items) (Box 12, Folder 1-12)
  This is a small series, which includes a number of items relating to Bernrieder's involvement in politics. The bulk of the series includes clippings relating to the 1932 elections and the Democratic National Convention, which was held in Houston in 1928. Additional materials include correspondence with Chesley Jurney and George Graves. For related materials, see the files in the Franklin Roosevelt Visit Series.
  - Clippings, 1929 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Convention--Graves, George, 1927-1962 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Convention--Miscellaneous, 1928-1932 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Convention--Report, 1928 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Convention--Souvenir, 1928 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Jurney, Chesley, 1927-1935 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928-1962 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Smith, Alfred--Photograph, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Franklin Roosevelt Visit, 1933-1980, (495 items) (Box 12-13, 16, Framed)
  The bulk of this series relates to Franklin Roosevelt's visit to Houston in 1936. Included are documents relating to planning the various events, such as the parade and visit to the San Jacinto Battlefield. There is some correspondence with various Democratic politicians, including Marvin McIntyre, Alfred E. Smith, Jr. and Henry Breckinridge. These materials were labeled by Bernrieder as belonging with the Roosevelt visit material.
  - Banner, 1936 (Box 16)
  - Battlefield Plans, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Boat List, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Breckinridge, Henry, 1933-1936 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Committees, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Cooper, Beauford O., 1970 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1980 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - McIntyre, Marvin, 1933-1937 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Memorabilia, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936 (Box 12, Folder 26)